so
[Music]
hello and welcome everyone to actin flap
livestream number 32.3
it's december 16th 2021 and we are
really excited to be here with connor
one of the
authors today we'll just jump right into
it
our goal is to be
learning and discussing this awesome
paper stochastic chaos and markov
blankets from 2021 with carl firsten
connor heinz kyle ulzhoffer lancelot
acosta and thomas parr
and we had a
0.1.2
on this paper and today we're just
excited to have a.3 so we'll have a
presentation by conor when we'll all be
providing our regime of attention and
writing down any questions and comments
we have and writing any questions in the
live chat if we would like and then we
will have a discussion to kind of
follow up on the presentation so connor
thank you for joining and please take it
away
great thanks daniel thanks for having me
i'm really happy to be back this is my
second time
on the stream so it's nice to be here
um okay i'm gonna share my whole screen
and now
here's the presentation
looks good thank you looks good okay
cool so yeah could you maybe right where
it says hide meet jitsi is sharing your
screen
yep and then
hit hide yep
the whole thing disappeared but then
yeah okay perfect we're back right yep
thank you
um yeah so as daniel said i'll be
presenting on um this paper
that was published um this fall in
entropy called stochastic chaos and
markup blankets
and
it's really great that you guys have
already gone through the paper in detail
from what i remember from watching some
of the past streams so we don't have to
go through every single
equation in every figure
because you guys have already kind of
covered it very thoroughly but we can
dive in
with as much technical detail as anyone
wants to so i'm kind of going to give
broad strokes of the paper and also
frame it in the context of other
literature that's come out on similar
topics in the past few months like oh
yes
a bunch of literature has been published
on the same sort of themes
um so that'll kind of help contextualize
what i consider to be the main
contributions of the paper
and
there's both methodological and
theoretical ones so there's a lot to
talk about here and
as daniel said i guess afterwards we'll
do this discussion but if um either of
you has question or anyone in in the
jitsi has questions during it like feel
free from my end i'm fine being
interrupted but whatever the format is
fine
um
okay so without further ado i'll get
started so just a quick introduction to
me
so i'm one of the co-authors on the
paper and i'm a phd student based in
constance germany where i'm supervised
by ian cousin who is a kind of um
leading
scientist in the fields of complex
systems and collective animal behavior
so he's the head of the department of
collective behavior at the mox planck
institute for animal behavior
and um so yeah we
in constance we're basically building a
kind of hub for the study of complex
systems and collective behavior in
particular then i'm also co-advised by
the lead author on the paper who's carl
fristen who kind of came up with the
fundamental uh premise of a lot of the
concepts in the paper like the free
energy principle bayesian mechanics
markov blankets stuff like that
so the outline um first i'll talk about
the motivations for the paper some of
the contextual literature
and then i'll summarize what i consider
to be the main takeaways but there's a
lot of different perspectives on this
paper so we these aren't by any means
the only way to interpret the paper
and then all
in the interest of just kind of getting
us all in the same conceptual footing
i'll review stochastic processes and in
particular a special interpretation of
stochastic processes called the
helmholtz decomposition which is
something that you guys have already
talked about in the past streams
here quite a bit
and then i will step through the primary
moves of the paper in my mind and i'll
leave out i'm not going to go through
every single figure like i said but i'll
just step through what i consider to be
the primary moves
so in this past year a bunch of work has
come out on the general theme of
bayesian mechanics
um so
if you want to kind of look at this
paper in the context of other work i
would say that the major works are
things like the bayesian mechanics for
stationary processes which just
last week was finally published in
proceedings a of the royal society so
we're very happy about that and that
kind of established the fundamental
mathematical formalism for bayesian
mechanics and the conditions under which
you can
apply a bayesian mechanical lens to
dynamical systems random dynamical
systems so this is something that's been
covered in previous live streams that
and a few of which lance and i were were
attendants at
there's another great paper that's a
pre-print right now by miguel aguilera
and some of his colleagues
that studies very similar grounds that's
covered in this first paper basically
studying the the necessary conditions
for bayesian mechanics and
in particular
uncovering what's known as the
synchronization manifold um and studying
that in the context of simple linear
gaussian systems
and then finally there's this paper also
produced also in the same special issue
of entropy
as the present paper called memory and
markov blankets and that's again
studying how markup blankets actually
evolved through time
i mentioned these three papers because
they all study bayesian mechanics and in
particular they're all focused primarily
on linear systems so systems
that are often in the stochastic
literature called uh linear diffusion
processes or ornstein ulenbek processes
um so that's a really deep common thread
to all of them is they leverage the
mathematical tractability of these
simple linear systems to get really nice
analytic proofs about when bayesian
mechanics exists and when it doesn't
i i say the primary focus on linear
systems because in for instance basic
mechanics for stationary processes the
mathematical derivations actually apply
to any processes that have a gaussian
steady state not only linear ones but
the primary examples used in that paper
were all linear systems i mean there are
a few non-linear ones but the focus and
the the tight derivations focused on
linear systems
um so given that kind of contextual
background now we can talk about the
main takeaways of this paper stochastic
chaos and markup blankets
so the the first main thing is basically
taking a random dynamical system in this
case we're taking a stochastic version
of the lorenz attractor and we're trying
to basically apply the lens of bayesian
mechanics to it so the same thing that
these previous papers have done to look
at the paper from the perspective or
look at the system from the perspective
of how is the system look as if it's
forming beliefs about other subsets of
variables in its environment so that's
what something we also call the physics
of sentience how can physical systems
not necessarily things we typically
think of as sentient actually exhibit
the hallmarks of something like
biological
computation or representation
the second main takeaway is
finding that you can fit the helmholtz
decomposition which is this
special
interpretation of stochastic processes
that we'll cover in the next few slides
how can you kind of learn that
decomposition automatically from data or
not from data but from stochastic
dynamical systems where the usual
tractability doesn't exist so that's a
big methodological contribution it
actually lays out a kind of the steps or
an algorithm for doing this
automatically for systems that lack the
usual analytic tractability like you get
with linear systems
and finally
i think another kind of big contribution
here that was kind of tucked into one of
the later sections of the papers was
pretty interesting
is a new result on the relationship
between the markov blanket and causal
coupling between systems so we basically
show that a markup blanket does not
always imply
uh causal relationships and vice versa
so the markov method is fundamentally a
statistical relationship that doesn't
always go hand in hand with a causal
relationship
so those are the main three takeaways
that i'll discuss today but there's a
few others that we can also dive into
that may have been covered in other live
streams
so um
to to do the
first goal of like basically deriving a
physics of sentience
we need to actually start with bayesian
mechanics as our goal and then from
there we'll get to the study of
stochastic processes so i'm going to
quick
first give an overview of bayesian
mechanics
the general idea of babes and appearance
is very i would say it can be described
very non-mathematically which is
basically you just have a system
that's embedded in some kind of ambient
environment
and crucially that system has an
interface with the environment it can
only exchange information with the
environment through some kind of sensory
uh or active interface so in the context
of
the the most popular use case for
bayesian mechanics that would be
something like a brain a nervous system
that's insulated from the world via
things like
muscular organs effector organs and then
sensory modalities so the interface is
comprised of the way we can impact the
world around us as well as the way that
we kind of absorb or are impressed by
information from the world
and then you can zoom in right and say
that a single cell has the same kind of
relationship where
intracellular processes are like the
equivalent of the brain you know this is
um genetic things going on with dna or
just intracellular
metabolic
cascades and then the interface would be
something like the cell membrane which
kind of mediates information and energy
transfer between the cells intracellular
contents
and then some extracellular environment
and then for from my perspective what
i'm interested in studying personally is
kind of zooming out and saying how can
you look at an entire system let's say a
school of fish or a flock of birds as if
the whole thing is a kind of internal
system that's insulated from some kind
of social or physical environment where
the interface here might not be as
simple as
um your skin or
uh
a
cell membrane but something more
embodied by other individuals maybe the
sensory interface between a group and
its surrounding are sensory or active
individuals and that's you know this is
very catered to my own interests but as
you know there's tons of people are
trying to apply the same framework to
all kinds of systems even like
socio-technical systems and societies
and stuff so it's a very generic
framework
that's the fundamental kind of partition
of the world that we're interested in
with bayesian mechanics and what
bayesian mechanics is saying is that if
you take these three sets of states
which i've now termed mu internal
b blanket that's the interface states
and then edda which is the external
world if you take that fundamental
three-way partition of the world
bayesian mechanics is just saying that
under certain conditions it looks as if
the internal states
are encoding the external states and the
thing that allows that encoding to
happen is a special function or a
manifold that's called the
synchronization map which just maps
information from the internal to the
external
and the the conditions for this
happening is basically that information
that gets to the internal world is
basically conditionally independent of
the external world when that
conditioning is done on the interface so
the interface kind of statistically
insulates the internal from the external
and with that at play you can actually
have the internal states look as if
they're encoding the external states
so that's the gist of bayesian mechanics
without leaving out as much math as i as
we possibly can
so then basic mechanics research first
asked the question
what are the necessary and sufficient
conditions for that map to exist so
that's something that
the earlier paper bayesian mechanics for
stationary processes that's what it
explicitly explored what are the
mathematical conditions for us to be
justified in saying yeah that map
actually exists
and once we've answered this first aim
of basic mechanics then we can try to
actually look for hallmarks of bayesian
mechanics in real systems biotic and
abiotic alike so those are the kind of
two that the first thing is what is
basic mechanics what allows it to exist
and then the second thing is saying once
we know those conditions we can actually
look for that in the real world
okay so
to do this proper analysis of a system
um to to identify this three-way
partition internal blanket external you
need basically a probability
distribution over the states of our
system so that's what's denoted with
this p
probably a distribution that tells you
for every setting of mu
b and eta internal blanket external
what's the probability of that
particular configuration
so that's a kind of a tall order getting
a full probability distribution for any
system is not
um
is not trivial you know for some systems
it is trivial but for most of things
we're interested in we usually don't
have access to that
so um that's why a lot of the work in
this field so far has not been really
applied to actual empirical data because
it's so theoretical at this point and
very like in silico um so we're still at
that stage where we're still figuring
things out theoretically and we haven't
moved to like empirical application yet
mainly because of these these issues of
finding what that probability
distribution um so
that's basic mechanics and now to move
from there to stochastic processes we're
motivated by the fact that in the case
we need to find this probability
distribution
and the internal blanket and external
states change over time i.e they're
dynamic
then we need to move to the realm of
stochastic processes and the reason that
is is because stochastic differential
equations
are the mathematical construct that
allow us to write down a probability
distribution over variables that change
over time
so a way to express that is using a
stochastic differential equation this is
the basic
a basic kind of abstract formalism for
understanding probability distributions
over paths or over sequences of states
over time that's really what a
stochastic process is but we like to
formally
summarize that that probability
distribution using this kind of
differential equation and all this
differential equation is saying is that
the rate of change of some state
is a function of the state
so it's basically a deterministic
function of the state
where where i'm going is a function of
where i am
plus some random noise and the random
noise is just
basically there to
to incorporate the fact that i don't
know my position
with certainty over time i have some
sense that's given by that deterministic
flow but overall there's uncertainty in
where i'll be next so we capture all
that uncertainty with this thing noise
and that's the basic structure of any
stochastic process or stochastic
differential equation
okay so
now we're going to zoom in on to this
this flow component which is the
deterministic part of the stochastic
process so here after when i say flow or
drift we're referring to the
deterministic part of this flow equip of
this stochastic differential equation
we're going to take that and we're going
to expand it to give it a new
interpretation that will allow us to get
back to our original goal which is
writing down a probability distribution
so that we can do bayesian mechanics
so the the interpretation that allows us
to make those moves is called the
helmholtz decomposition and it's
basically saying that any
that any flow
of a stochastic differential equation
there are a few conditions on the flow
that we can get into they're kind of
technical conditions but if this flow
meets those basic conditions which are
quite general then you can decompose it
into the sum of two parts
one is called the reversible part of the
flow and the other one is called the
irreversible part of the flow
and we'll get into now what that
actually means so the the first one is
called the reversible part of the flow
and it can basically be seen as a
gradient flow
towards the maximum of the probability
density of the whole system so that
probability distribution we talked about
at the beginning it has peaks and
valleys right there's areas of higher
density and lower density this
reversible part of the flow is just
telling the system bring me to the local
maxima or to the peaks of that
probability density
this is also referred to as dissipative
or time reversible because a system
that's driven by this gradient flow has
time um
reversibility or time symmetry in the
sense that if you run one version of the
process forwards in time it'll look the
same ran backwards
and the important part here is that it's
tightly related to the noise or the
random fluctuations that we talked about
from earlier so the strength of the
force that pushes you towards
the maxima of your probability density
is directly proportional to the
amplitude or the variance of the noise
so that's a very interesting concept um
that might be a little counterintuitive
at first but basically those random
fluctuations that we're adding
to the the flow in the um langevin
equation
how big those fluctuations are
determines how quickly or with what
force we get to the probability density
is maxima
which you might think that's a little
weird why would more noise actually make
us get to where we're going faster
wouldn't that push us away from our path
but if you think about averages and
think about the density of paths trying
to get somewhere in probably density the
more noise you have actual more chances
the system has to kind of explore state
space and then reach its eventual um
average like steady state density faster
so that's one part is this um
gradient flow this dissipative flow
that's who's whose strength is is uh
proportional to the amplitude of random
fluctuations
and then secondly we have this more
interesting thing which is called the
conservative or time irreversible
component also called the solenoidal
flow
and this is mediated by this
anti-symmetric operator called q
and this basically doesn't point either
in the direction of the minima or the
maxima of the probability density of the
system but rather it points you along
the iso contours of equal probability of
that density so this is the kind of
circus component of the flow
and it's very interesting from the
perspective of thermodynamics because
systems with
this time irreversibility they um
exhibit positive entry production for
instance
and they uh and they basically have
conservative dynamics
so here's an example on the left of the
stochastic process that's just driven by
gradient flow with some noise on top of
it and you can see that it's kind of
ascending or running parallel to the the
probability density and then on the
right we have a deterministic system
that's just driven by solenoidal flow
and it kind of acts like a celestial
body like a planet that's orbiting on
some center of gravity
uh and i should say that the blue
background on each plot is basically
showing how high the probability density
is of the states um at each point in
state space so this is just a two
dimensional system
so the helmholtz decomposition is saying
that you can take these two components
and together they form the full dynamic
of any stochastic system
so the full dynamic has components of
trying to get to the maxima of the
probability density and then it also has
components of kind of surfing the iso
contours of probability density and all
of this is subject to random
fluctuations that are kind of knocking
it off the path so you can get kind of
rich dynamics with just this very simple
decomposition of any system's flow
um so this is another way that we can
visualize these things in terms of
vector fields so on the left i'm showing
the solenoidal flow like the strength of
that component at each point in state
space so x and y are just the two levels
of some two-dimensional random variable
here are the components of the
dissipative flow
and you can see that they're parallel to
the gradients that pull you towards or
away from the center of the probability
density
and then if you add these two things
together
then you get the the force that's
driving the system at every point in
state space which is this combination of
this kind of orbiting um fluctuation as
well as this thing that's pulling it
towards the center and just a kind of
technical note the ra the reason that
the dissipative flow looks like it's
pointing away from the center in the
middle plot
but it's pointing to the center and the
right plot is because there's a minus
sign in front of the dissipative
operator on the right paw so that's an
important thing that often uh confuses
people
so now we've done this decomposition we
have this gradient flow we have the
solenoidal flow
um and and the the thing that brings us
back to
bayesian mechanics is this important
point that i left out which is that the
gradient fill in the solenoidal flow
they don't just operate on the state of
the system but they operate
on the gradient of the probability
density which is given by this kind of
weird i slash j operator which we can
just call the surprisal
so the surprisal is defined as the
negative log of the probability density
it's also known in physics as a scalar
potential and this just says how
basically tells you how far away you are
in some sense from the center of the
probability density it's saying what is
the local curvature right now how steep
is the probability landscape at the
point i am right now
so this in turn these are the things
that scale the the dissipative and the
solenoidal operators and this thing in
turn can be formally related to the
steady state distribution of the process
this probability density over mu
b and eta that we were originally
interested in so it because it's the
negative log of that density you can
exponentiate its negative and you get
yourself back to the density and that's
excluding something that's called a
partition function but that density is
called the non-equilibrium steady state
density
and the existence of that
is kind of fundamental to the whole free
energy principle bayesian mechanics
thing if a system has this nest density
then the system can achieve bayesian
mechanics
and another important point is if q is
non-zero
the system truly is non-equilibrium if
it is zero if the q does not exist and
there's only dissipative currents the
system is known as an equilibrium system
and it just has an equilibrium steady
state so the q is basically what
mediates all the things that we're
interested in biological systems like
the breaking of detail balance
positive entropy production rate and
time irreversibility that's all kind of
built baked into the system with q
um so the main point of all these slides
on stochastic processes helmholtz
decomposition is just the fact that that
deterministic flow component of the
longitude equation
can be rewritten in terms of gradients
of its log stationary density so it
looks as if any stochastic process is
basically being dragged towards its
stationary density subject to random
noise and these solenoidal um components
that kind of drive it along the iso
contours
so we can now kind of take the steps
required to rewrite our full lines of n
equation using this new interpretation
so first you have this flow operator
which is just a combination of the
irreversible and reversible components
then you can plug that into our
expression for f which is the flow so
it's the flow operator times the
gradients of the log density the
negative log density and then minus this
extra term that i'll talk about in in a
few minutes
and then you can just combine all this
together
plug it back into the login equation and
now we have an expression for the login
equation namely the rate of change of
the state in terms of a gradient descent
on the um on this surprisal so basically
all this is saying is that a system
looks like it's trying to minimize the
surprisal of its states i.e find itself
in parts of state space that are the
least surprising or have the highest
probability
so as i just mentioned there's this
extra term that we haven't talked about
it's kind of called this housekeeping or
correction term and this i think has
come up in a few of the the past live
streams if i remember correctly and this
is going to be really important for the
current paper kind of mediates all the
interesting things that we see in in
things like stochastic chaos so
this is called what carl calls in the
paper the housekeeping term
and it only arises in the case that
those solenoidal and dissipative
matrices depend on the state of the
system
so for these earlier papers we were
talking about like the bayesian
mechanics
for stationary processes and the
miguel's paper as well as
the memory markov blankets paper those
three papers for the most part assume
that these matrices were constant in the
sense that they don't depend on the
states
that's what makes a system a linear
versus a non-linear system if these
matrices are constant then the system is
linear if they are not constant in the
states i.e they depend on the part of
state space you're in
then it's a non-linear system and this
housekeeping term is non-zero it
actually has some influence on the
dynamics
so this is something that is figures
into the current paper on the lorenz
attractor so lorenz attractor which
we'll get into later is a non-linear
system so this housekeeping term becomes
non-zero
and for if anyone's technically
interested that's just what it looks
like it's it's basically a type of
matrix field divergence which is a
mouthful but it's basically a sum of
partial derivatives of the matrix field
across different
state variables
so given that we can now in in the case
of a non-linear system where the q
matrix actually depends on the state
now we're showing the solenoidal
operator as a function of state space
and you can see that now the solenoidal
flow actually depends on which which
part of the xy plane you're in
here denoted x1 x2
the dissipative operator i've kept
constant just to be simple
and then you have additionally this
housekeeping term
that is also a function of state space
and it's kind of actually counteracting
in some sense the dissipative operator
and it's a weird combination of kind of
flows that are pulling you towards the
center as well as away from the center
and then the full dynamic is going to be
this combination between a housekeeping
term
the solenoidal term and the dissipative
term altogether so these are the kind of
systems that you're going to more likely
encounter in the real world service
because most real-world systems are
non-linear they can't be described with
nice uh ornstein ulenbach processes
where the housekeeping term disappears
okay so that was our big detour into
helmholtz decomposition and it was a lot
of math and theory but it'll actually
become
concrete when we apply it to that to the
lorenz attractor so now let's go back to
our our desired um goal of getting that
probability distribution
so we want a probability distribution
over mu internal states blanket states
external states so that we can do
bayesian mechanics
and now we're going to say that our
system of interest x is just
a 3 a 3d system a 3 vector that's
comprised of internal blanket external
at every time so we want to have a 3d
probability distribution over those
variables
so once we have that probability
distribution we can basically do what's
called
marginalize the density and find
conditional density so we can say give
me the conditional density over internal
given blanket states give me the
conditional density over external given
blanket states those two densities are
theoretically the things that get mapped
to each other through the
synchronization map so that's something
i didn't really mention in the beginning
with this theoretical kind of more
semantic description of bayesian
mechanics
but technically basic mechanics has to
do with conditional densities it says
tell me condition on some level of the
blanket states what is the most likely
value of the internal states and if you
know that and you have a synchronization
map you can kind of guess the most
likely value of the external states
condition on blanket states so the
synchronization map is really mapping
the two conditional densities to each
other
quick question
so at that point
can we do because you've used phrases
like zoom in
and zoom out and when you talk about
decomposition
do we know
where
on on the scaler
that
will this tell us where
something is
focused or versus something that's
looking at horizons
do you know what i'm saying like can we
tell
what the field is based on this that
that the thing is
trying to map
and when you say
horizons do you mean like temporal
horizons or do you mean more spatial you
know i'm i'm saying like can we tell
whether it's
it's it's zooming in on a focal point or
whether it's it's looking at a larger
picture
oh i see time wise and and map wise so
yeah so the the map technically is very
focal in the sense that
i haven't shown it in the lower right
because i didn't want to get too
technical but the synchronization map
technically
maps um the sufficient statistics of the
densities together so it maps a
particular point on a statistical
manifold
so when i say statistical manifold i
mean a space that is not spanned by the
values of the system but actually by the
expected values or the averages of the
system so it says
on average
the internal states will get mapped to
the external states so in that sense
it's kind of a point because you're
saying i'm point i'm i'm mapping from a
most likely value or from an average
to another average on the other side of
the blanket but it's so in that sense
you're kind of doing a dimensionality
reduction because the map is not defined
for any particular little
fluctuation of the internal or the
external like some particular instance
but it's actually really defined on this
average level so you're only going to be
seeing the inference when you take
averages across multiple noisy
realizations
um connor if i could ask one more
question to kind of lock in the gains of
this great section is it fair to say
that the synchronization map is
literally the internal states map of the
external states territory
yeah exactly okay
the synchronization map will
take any internal state and it will map
it
into
a map like it'll map it into a space and
that space is a map of the the external
states territory and it might not be
correct you know it could be off but
it's basically taking any internal state
and it's projecting it into a
representation and that representations
um metric space like when i move around
in that represented space is supposed to
mirror how external states are actually
moving
um and the key point of the
synchronization map is the map in the
territory will only be aligned
on average but for any given particular
instance of the internal states that
guess where that place it gets mapped to
on the on the map on the representation
might be arbitrarily far
from the true external state that's
going on at that time but on average
they'll be exactly on top of each other
and there's one
comment in the chat from miguel aguilera
so i'm gonna read it to you conor and
you can address it now or if it comes
at a better time later then address it
then so miguel writes
great introduction of the helmholtz
decomposition
how general is the housekeeping lambda
term can it account for any non-linear
systems with higher order terms for
example larger than quadratic
that's a great question um yes it
totally can
uh
so if we go back to it
where was it
let's address it now if that's okay with
me done
yeah
yeah so if you look at this a
housekeeping term it's defined as this
divergence of the matrix field
and it's a sum of the partial
derivatives of the flow operator um so
now i'm talking about the last equation
on the slide the flow operator again is
the q minus the gamma
so those partial derivatives if they're
higher order than quadratic
they will
they will have
uh non-linear terms right so if you're
taking
uh the partial derivative of something
that has a third or a fourth order then
the partial derivative itself will be
non-linear so all that means is that the
housekeeping term itself will be
non-linear in the states so the
housekeeping term is also a function of
the states and in this case with higher
order ex
more than quadratic terms then you'll
just get a not an appropriately
non-linear housekeeping term um so for
instance if we go back to this slide
in the third um
the third column the housekeeping term
because i made the q matrix the
solenoidal matrix
a second order in the states i.e there's
an interaction between x1 and x2 a
multiplicative interaction the
housekeeping term becomes linear in one
of the two states so it's just a simple
linear function of x1 and x2
if however we are to imagine that either
q
or gamma gamma is the dissipative
operator i made it constant for now but
if one of those had a higher order term
like a x to the third term or x square
x1 squared times x2 then the
housekeeping term would also have now a
non-linear term and now housekeeping
would be non-linear in the in the state
space and there's nothing wrong with
that it would just mean the housekeeping
term would be non-linear and the
dynamics would be even more complex um
yeah that's a great question miguel
thanks
and if i could ask some follow-up
housekeeping questions so
uh one can the housekeeping
be non-differentiable or what if there's
some function that doesn't have a nice
derivative and the second part is
what does the housekeeping turn
term represent
for a given example system and how is it
different than the regular helmholtz
decomposition
that's a good good question
um so the first question is
about differentiability so i mentioned
in the beginning that for a system to
have these nice things we were talking
about like to basically be applied to
the helmholtz decomposition to be
applied to it etc
one of the conditions is that the flow
function that f of x is a smooth
function of the states so as in
basically means it's differentiable
everywhere as long as the flow is
differentiable it implies that all the
sub components are also differentiable
if my memory of calculus serves me well
so basically it means that q will be
differentiable which means that all its
higher order derivatives are also
differentiable so basically um
the the the very premise of this
decomposition assumes that things are
differentiable so that that problem
shouldn't arise or if there's
non-differentiable
flow function
then you're right all these things will
have discontinuities and and i don't
think the solution or there there are
any guarantees that the decomposition
even applies in that case
um
the second question can you sorry can
you remind me with the second one oh
sorry yeah the interpretation of the
housekeeping term that's a really good
question i this is something we talked a
lot about with carl um when
when we discussed this paper at a tnb
meeting like how do you interpret this
because the solenoidal flow right i can
imagine it's you're going along the iso
contours dissipative makes sense you're
going up and down the gradients of the
density itself but the housekeeping term
is this weird thing where it has to do
with the derivatives
of the state-dependent solenoidal and
dissipative flow
i don't know how to interpret it to be
honest with you in terms of like one of
these nice kind of orthogonality just
because it's not an orthogonalization of
this of the state space it's it's a
mixture of both state-dependent
solenoidal and dissipative terms
the the one thing he did say that that
carl said to us that uh that we'll come
to later is that the housekeeping term
in the case of chaotic dynamics is
actually what mediates the wandering
seemingly non-steady state-ish uh
behavior of things like the lorenz
attractor so the lorenz attractor seems
to kind of go on these itinerant
wandering so that are arbitrarily far
from its steady state density whatever
that state density is because again we
don't know what it is and basically the
housekeeping term in this case
can push the system away from the
gradients of the log density
and also away from the level sets of the
iso contours of the density given by the
solenoid flow so an example of that is
actually here right where you see in
kind of the main
xy planes of the if you compare the red
plot to the purple plot the red arrows
are actually pointing sometimes in the
opposite arrows of the purple arrows so
one interpretation is that for
sufficiently complex systems sometimes
they'll actually be quite strong
components of the flow that are driving
it away
from the the probability density's
maxima
so this might actually if you want to
try to interpret this in the context of
biological systems systems sometimes
seem to wander very far away from
what in a greedy sense would be the the
best state to be an i.e a local mode of
the probability density and this
housekeeping term can sometimes drive
the system into long wandering sojourns
that are far away from those local
maxima
um and and it's the strength of that
housekeeping term versus the dissipative
term that carl argues is actually the
the the um helmholtz decomposition
take on chaotic behavior so chaotic
behavior is when things wander
arbitrarily far basically because the
housekeeping term dominates and pushes
things away from the modes of the
density
that was the closest that i got to like
a kind of interpretation of the
housekeeping term but it's a really good
question i would be curious to hear what
other people um have to say about that
um okay so
yes so right this is where we work so
we're talking about the synchronization
map that's where we want to get to we
want to get to being able to write down
those conditional densities so that we
can map them to each other and then
imbue our system with some form of
sentience
or at least a sentient interpretation so
how do we get this density so this
brings us to the first major
contribution of the paper which is a new
method for approximating a system where
we don't have that density so for
instance the system we're about to talk
about the lorenz attractor we don't know
what the probability density is so we're
going to use
a new method proposing this paper to
approximate that density
um and the method used to approximate
the density relies on a combination of
polynomial regression as well as the
helmholtz decomposition so that's why i
just spent so much time going through
the helmholtz decomposition because this
new method proposed by the paper for
fitting the density relies on the
helmholtz decomposition as well as
basically
some
some statistical inference techniques or
polynomial regression
so now we're going to actually make
things specific and dive into a
particular system
so the lorenz attractor
a phase space portrait of it is shown in
the top left is a famous deterministic
dynamical system that exhibits what's
known as chaos and again i'm gonna not
go too into depth here to save time and
um
last time in one of the early early
streams daniel gave a very nice
explanation of chaotic behavior but it
basically means
when you very slightly alter the initial
conditions of the system
the end up and resulting trajectory can
can can be arbitrarily far in state
space so if i start the system at
setting point one versus point one zero
one the resulting place that those two
trajectories end up can be super far
away from each other so it's quantified
um most often by analyzing what's known
as the eigenvalues of the jacobian or
the lyapunov x point um the sign of
which will tell you how far systems on
how far trajectories on average should
diverge and that's kind of the hallmark
of chaos
so that's the lorenz attractor it gives
these nice um kind of itinerant
wandering butterfly lobes when you look
at its trajectories over time the
interesting property is that no same one
trajectory is is the same for a slightly
different initial condition that's why
we call it chaotic
what we study in this
paper is exactly that deterministic
chaotic system but we just add noise
onto its flow function so that's what's
represented with the equations here so
we can call it the stochastic lorenz
attractor it's kind of uh it's not um
it's not
been characterized super rigorously as
much as the lorenz attractor has been so
it's a kind of interesting experimental
stochastic process to
to investigate here so on the bottom
right we see the original stochastic
lorenz flows which is a nonlinear
deterministic dynamical system that's
that f x and what we're doing here is
we're just perturbing the system at
every time with a little random gaussian
fluctuation that's what's represented by
omega
and i've bolded everything here to
represent that where now we're dealing
with a vector space of state so we're
dealing with x1 x2 x3 it's not just a
single variable but it's a 3d um system
okay so now we can get into the major
moves of the actual paper so the first
approach is to say okay we know about
this helmholtz decomposition thing let's
try to rewrite the lorenz attractor as
if it's doing a gradient
ascent on a log probability density or a
gradient descent on on surprisal
so an important thing to note here is
the surprisal as well as the flow
operator the q and the gamma are state
dependent and as we know now from our
discussion of the housekeeping term
we're going to get that extra lambda
term
because the system is state dependent
and you can just look at the flows from
lorenz attractor to see that very
clearly so for instance f of x is not
just first order in the state so that
would mean it would be a linear system
but for instance the the flow of x2
depends on the multiplicative
interaction between x1 and x3 and
likewise the flow of x3 depends on the
multiplicative interaction between x1
and x2 that state dependence
will be exactly recapitulating the fact
that q and gamma will not be a constant
function of the states and because of
that we'll also get this housekeeping
term this big lambda on the on the side
so that's why the lorenz attractor was
chosen as opposed to an ou process
exactly because it has this
non-linearity the state dependence
so if we want to write down an ou
process
and this is a decomposition that people
like miguel know very well by now you
can just write it down as this linear
matrix function which is just q which is
a matrix
minus gamma and other matrix multiplied
by the gradients of a gaussian
probability density a log gaussian
okay so the first approach um to tackle
decomposing the lorenz attractor as if
it's doing a gradient descent is
basically fitting that dependency so
fitting q and gamma using polynomial
expansions so assume we didn't know the
true lorenz flows and we just want to
basically fit okay if i want to express
the lorenz flows in terms of a q and
gamma what would i do the first approach
is to
first of all take our state space which
is x1 x2 x3 and expand it in terms of
polynomial um basis functions which
again is something i think was covered
in an earlier live stream it's also
known as a taylor expansion where we're
saying i'm going to express each state
of the system not as x1 x2 x3 but things
like x1 squared x1 x2 x1 x2 x3 all these
interaction terms and higher order terms
and then i'm going to say
find me a function that maps from that
high order basis in terms of polynomial
expansions to the coefficients of q and
gamma respectively
and i'm also going to model this
surprisal function
which is the negative log of the density
as a function of the polynomial states
so the the problem of polynomial
regression is just finding finding the
coefficients here q and h
that
need to be multiplied by these
polynomial expansions in order to fit
the observed flow as as best possible so
this is a very common technique used in
data science right instead of just doing
a linear regression between
um let's say housing prices and the size
of the house you add in higher order
terms like the squared size of the house
or the size of the house times the size
of the pool or whatever so it's like a
very classic thing is to use polynomial
expansions to get more expressive
functions to explain some observed data
so we're doing the same thing here
except that the data we're trying to
explain is the actual flow of the system
so what the first move of the paper is
is to actually do this fitting process
and to and figure out that you can
rewrite
the deterministic lorenz system
as if it's doing a gradient descent on
this surpriso function but as we'll see
later it's actually not a proper
surprisal so we can just call it a
potential function for now and basically
that the solution is a second order
function of the state so there's a
multiplicative term between x1 and x2
with coefficient h5 and then there's a
linear term in x3
and then what this means is that if you
do this for the deterministic system so
you actually assume the random
fluctuations go to zero then what you
can do is rewrite the parameters of the
lorenz attractor which are given by
sigma beta and rho these are the classic
ways that people just parameterize the
lorenz attractor and you know certain
settings of row and beta lead to chaos
and different kinds of attractors
you can rewrite them in terms of the
coefficients of the helmholtz
decomposition so that's the first major
move is that this hum holds
decomposition can be used
to write down the system's flows as if
it's doing a gradient descent on a
potential function
there's a problem with this though which
is that
if we look at that potential it's
actually not a proper probability
distribution so this isn't really
bayesian mechanics this first move all
it's saying is that we can
force the helmholtz decomposition to
explain the flow function of the lorentz
attractor but the resulting surprisal
function we're left with is actually not
a proper probability distribution
and you if you just analyze that
equation and try to interpret it like a
probability uh function it won't
actually work
so that has to do with whether it's
positive the gradients are positive
definite essentially
so that motivates the next move
which is um where we don't try to
approximate the lorenz attractor exactly
but we try to approximate what car
refers to as a laplace approximation to
the steady state density
so here instead of saying okay let's
rewrite the lorenzo tractor as helmholtz
decomposed let's assume that the lorenz
attractor is dragged towards a steady
state that's gaussian so the nest is a
multivariate gaussian and if we force
that assumption on and then use our
polynomial regression what is the kind
of resulting
coefficients that we'll get because now
we're forcing the system to look as if
it's doing a gradient descent on a
proper surprisal function or a gradient
ascent on a proper probability
distribution
um
so if you do that constraint and then
you fit the helmholtz decomposition so
again we're fitting the coefficients of
the flow operator q and gamma in terms
of the states using polynomial
expansions of the states and we're
constraining the surprisal function to
be quadratic i.e the steady state is
gaussian
then we basically create not a perfect
recapitulation of the stochastic lorenz
system but something that looks like the
lorenz system with this weird constraint
that it has to be occupying on average a
gaussian steady state which is not
necessarily true of the real lorenz
system that's an interesting move here
um and then what you get is again what
is referred to as the laplace
approximation into the stochastic
lorentz system which can be validated in
terms of how close it is to the real
lorenz system using things like the
hausdorff dimension which is a
quantification of the fractal
dimensionality of the system so it's
very well known that lorenz attractor
basically lives on a fractal uh
sub-manifold of its ambient state space
which is quantified by a fractal
hausdorff dimension or a non-integer
halsdorf dimension and that's just a
function of again of the eigenvalues of
the jacobian of the mate of the flow and
then he also validates the uh the
approximation quality by just looking at
how correlated the approximate flow is
using this polynomial method with the
true flow which is on the x-axis of that
correlation plot
and then on the right hand we have some
example trajectories of this laplace
approximated lorenz system
so this is a very interesting um kind of
plot because it's showing that even
though the the underlying gauss
underlying steady state density is a
multivariate gaussian
you can see that the actual trajectories
of the system don't necessarily look
like they're just neatly sitting or
wandering around that gaussian state
again because of the solenoidal flow and
because of that housekeeping term which
is very large in this case the
trajectories of the system look as if
they're making very like itinerant
wandering trajectories but on average if
you're to take a very infinite time
observation of the system the system
would still look as if it sits on a
gaussian steady state
so that's like the first i would say
major move of the paper is doing this
laplace approximate uh
gaussian version of the lorenz attractor
the stochastic lorenz attractor which
anecdotally has some features of the
lorenz attractor like it has these two
lobes and all of these
quantifications kind of make it
correlated but it's not exactly the
lorenz attractor because we're putting
constraints on it
um
that was a lot of information is are
there any comments or questions so far
okay so i'll just keep going
um so importantly
now that we've rewritten the the nest
density as if it's gaussian
we can use it to read off conditional
independent structure i.e the markov
blanket
and the reason that is is is uh obvious
basically from earlier papers like this
uh
bayesian mechanics for stationary
processes and miguel's paper on um
on also on linear diffusion systems
where basically you can just look at the
hessian or the inverse of the covariance
matrix and you can use that to read off
conditional independence i.e to read off
the mark of blanket
and that is only that simple
relationship between the inverse
covariance and the markov blanket only
obtains because of the gaussian nature
of the steady state density
so that's why the laplace approximation
works here or is a nice move to make
because it means we can then
write down or read off the markup
blanket very easily and so the lower
right is showing that the hessian and
the covariance matrix and you can so the
white here means very low values so what
we immediately see is that there's
basically a markov blanket between the
first and the third states
um conditioned on the on the second
states or actually sorry rather that the
first and second states are both
conditionally independent of the third
state
so there's kind of a markov blanket
between those two and and the third
state this one isn't as nice as the
coupled system as we'll see further
because it's actually not clear what the
blanket states are here this more seems
just like marginal marginal uh lack of
correlation
um but
so even though there's the like the
third and second states are also kind of
conditionally independent you can still
treat the second state as a blanket
state and you can basically parameterize
a density over the first state given the
second state so here we're writing down
a synchronization map between the first
and third states and this is symmetric
so
first can infer third or third current
for a thirst uh first but the
conditioning the blanket state is the
second state
so you can kind of see that if i just
take the instantaneous value of the
third state it's in some way performing
a guess or making an estimate about the
most likely value of the first state and
this relationship goes vice versa and
the only reason we can write down that
function that maps between the first and
the third is again because we have an
expression for the covariance matrix
which follows from the laplace
approximation or the gaussian
approximation to this uh stochastic
lorenz attractor
so um once that's been done the laplace
approximation
then the next move is kind of
it's not a full analysis but it's
showing that you can
extend this to non-gaussian steady
states and kind of make higher order
approximations which might be called
density learning so in a case when you
don't know you don't have a parametric
swarm for the state state density
you can parameterize the surprise
surprisal function and the helmholtz
decomposition in such a way that you
know that the resulting density is a
proper probability distribution but you
don't necessarily know what its neat
parametric form is so the way he does
this is basically by parameterizing the
quadratic or the potential as quadratic
but the covariance or the hessian of
that quadratic potential is state
dependent so it's almost like you're
fitting locally linear um
synchronization maps to different parts
in the state space or you're fitting
locally gaussian approximations so the
way it does this is essentially
i have a efficient parameterization of
the covariance matrix of my steady state
but that covariance is actually changing
as a function of state space whereas in
gaussians the covariance by definition
is constant
though
by doing this you can basically achieve
a nicer
approximation to the true stochastic
lorenz system
where all the conditional densities are
still
gaussian but the full multivariate
density is not necessarily calcium
so that's basically what's shown in the
right plot here is this higher order
learned stochastic lorenz system but
it's not clear in this case what the
synchronization map would be because the
synchronization map is not just going to
be a simple
uh function of the hessian because now
the hessian is is changing over state
space
connor can i ask a question here yeah
please so from the chat martin beal has
asked is this right
there are two approximations here one of
the dynamics and one of the stationary
state
uh yes i would say that the
approximations
um are intrinsically tied together
though because
what you're doing here
is you're
approximating the the
potential function
and then that approximation directly
factors into the approximation of the
flow right so you're fitting in this
case these kernel matrices these k
matrices as being state dependent so the
kernel matrix is basically a cholesky
factor of the covariance matrix or
really of the hessian here the precision
matrix
and the gradients of that will then
factor into the parameterization of the
flow right because the flow is defined
in terms of the helmholtz decomposition
which is
q minus gamma times the gradients of the
potential
so however you fit the stationary
density those coefficients that you fit
will also factor in
to the parameterization of the flow so
in this case in the upper left
i have the parameterization of the
the density this quadratic function if i
take the gradients with of that with
respect to the states it'll essentially
look like
k transpose k times x minus mu or
basically a precision weighted
prediction error right where k transpose
k is the precision and then x minus mu
is the deviation of
x from some mean vector
so you're doing all that all that
simultaneously you're doing both the
parameterization of the steady state as
well as the parameterization of the flow
but you're doing it all just by trying
to fit the flow
with these coefficients but for free
some of those coefficients you get out
you can use them to write down a
potential function
which can be converted to a stationary
density
does that make sense yes and just on
this slide what is pd
oh sorry positive definite okay
yep that's a good good point um so yeah
because these kernel matrices are
symmetric these k transpose times k
they're symmetric
um they're state dependent but they are
always symmetric it means that their
product will always be positive definite
which means that the
stationary density evaluated different
points in state space we'll always have
locally
be locally convex i.e there's going to
be some local mode but since that
pd matrix is changing over state space
you're going to basically have a
multimodal density but locally it'll be
unimodal that's another way of
expressing everything on the left side
okay so here's the more interesting part
where we can really start talking about
like the interesting bayesian mechanical
inferential interpretations
where now we have two coupled um lorenz
systems so again it's a stochastic
lorenz system but since we have two of
them that are talking to each other it's
really a six dimensional system so three
of one lorenzo tractor three of the
other and crucially we're coupling them
together
through
um the first
and fourth state so the the fourth state
of the system is really like the first
state of the second lorenz attractor if
that makes sense
so basically we're saying that
uh x1 the first state of one lorenz
attractor is talking to x4 which is the
first state of a second lorenz attractor
and so just by coupling with them with
this one state we're mediating kind of
the flow of information between these
two lorenz attractors
and now um
the next move is to go back to the
laplace approximation where we're
enforcing the surprisal function to be
quadratic a quadratic potential and now
we're applying it to this six
dimensional
um stochastic lorenz system so now we
are fitting this whole coupled system
with a 6d multivariate gaussian
and because of that gaussian constraint
we'll be able to read off the
synchronization map from the entries of
the hessian the inverse covariance
matrix so on the right what we have are
just example trajectories
from the coupled
lorenz systems
so this is what carl would call evidence
of a synchronization manifold in a in a
more in a less rigorous sense although
we'll get rigorous with it later but in
a more anecdotal sense you can see that
the systems are basically synchronized
with each other even they're only
connecting through one state they're
kind of surfing along similar sub
manifolds of their state space they're
kind of hugging each other
and um
again these other metrics like the very
bottom is just to show that the
approximated flow using this laplace
approximation plus
polynomial expansions is
qualitatively at least positively
correlated with the true flows of the
full nonlinear system that has no
gaussian approximation
and then the bayesian mechanics
interpretation comes in next where now
we again read off the markov blanket
uh
uh between that exists between two of
the lorenz attractors so here the upper
right is what i'm focusing on now here
the up the second two states state two
and state three are the internal states
of one lorenz attractor whereas states
five and six that dark blue box are the
internal states of the second lorenz
attractor
and they both share a pair of blanket
states which are x1 and x4
so the synchronization map is a map that
maps from
x2 and x3 to x5 and x6
where the mapping is done on the
conditional densities where the
conditioning is done on the sensory
state of either the first system or the
second system which is
respectively the active state of the
other so that's a little bit confusing
is basically the purple um sensory state
of the first system is actually the
active state of the second system and
vice versa
but the the
most bottom plot is basically showing
that at any given time
the internal states of one system are
making a best guess or a conditional
estimate about the external state which
are the internal states of the second
lorenz attractor so you basically have
two minds
little two-dimensional minds that are
making inferences about each other but
the inferences are done with respect to
these conditional densities where the
conditioning is done on the sensory
states
that's basically what all this all these
plots on the lower right are showing
um so that's that's the demonstration of
this inferential or sentience
interpretation
and then because as we said the uh the
full system is multivariate gaussian it
means all the conditional densities are
also gaussian and then you can literally
write down the
synchronization map as a linear function
of the states where that linear function
is given by appropriate sub matrices of
the full hessian which is the inverse
covariance and again because we're
fitting the
potential function using a polynomial
expansion it means that the hessian
function which is the double derivative
of the probability density with respect
to the states that will also be a
function of those polynomial
coefficients so the end result of all
that is basically that given this
polynomially approximated helmholtz
decomposition i can then write down the
synchronization map precisely in terms
of those coefficients that i fit
and then you can compute all these nice
things like a free energy function which
is basically a sum of accuracy or like
prediction errors and complexity which
is effectively a
prior penalty that penalizes how far the
uh
inferred expected state is from its
expectation under the full
um steady state density
so this is a nice
um this is a crucial result because it's
saying even if you don't know what the
true steady state of a system is you can
use polynomial expansions and a laplace
approximation to get something that
still has rich nonlinear dynamics but by
enforcing this gaussian constraint on it
you can then write down the
synchronization map using linear
functions and the form of that function
you know because you fit its
coefficients
by doing this helmholtz decomposition
okay so that's basically the main um
brunt of the uh of the paper
and ask a few questions so i have one
question and there's two in the chat so
the first question is
in this free energy equation on the
bottom pi is representing the particular
states but also we've seen free energy
minimization on pi representing policy
where
free energy minimization is involved in
the selection of affordances for policy
selection so what's the relationship
between free energy minimization of
particular states like the autonomous
states and how is that related to free
energy minimization as
planning as inference
yeah that's a great question so
yeah this has nothing to do with the
policy one it's just about pi which is
basically just saying the expected value
of the particular states which i should
have mentioned are
um the autonomous and the blanket states
so or the autonomous and the sensory
state so in this case the particular
states would be the two internal the
sensory and the active state
of one of those lorenz attractors where
its active state is actually the sensory
state of the other lorenz attractor so
they share you know they have one
overlap in terms of their blanket um so
this here is just saying that on average
the system is instantaneously minimizing
at all times this free energy functional
which is just saying
is penalizing particular states from how
far they are from their conditional
expected value that's the expectation of
pi given eta where the expectation is
taken under q um which is this
variational density that's parameterized
by the synchronization mapped internal
states
um
the the free the um
expected free energy which is what
you're talking about is how do you
write down a functional of
trajectories or paths of future
autonomous states that is minimized such
that you get the semblance of planning
behavior where you're penalizing not
something in terms of how far
instantaneous is but over a future
horizon how how much is the free energy
expected to deviate from the optimal
policy or path which is going to be a
sequence of autonomous states
um that is a more complex question that
has to basically do with
yeah free energy basically minimization
of actions which are
uh
under under certain assumptions sums of
surprisals over time
um and that's something that is not
treated at all in this paper but it is
explicitly treated in an upcoming paper
um that i believe is in review right now
where we explicitly make the connection
between the instantaneous free energy
minimization like we see here and then
this more temporally deep expected free
energy minimization but basically for
the present purposes of this paper
there's no relationship and there and
nothing can really be said here about
planning or temporally deep
uh free energy minimization
okay let's keep it on this slide and
i'll ask a few more questions in chat so
from martin
is the actual steady state distribution
of the lorenz attractor known
um
no
basically yeah okay
um i think there have been other
there's been other papers where they're
not using the stochastic lorenz system
but what they're using is
uh
the distributions of a bunch of lorenz
attractors so this is the difference
between i guess stochastic differential
equations and random dynamical systems
where
i'm randomizing a bunch of initial
conditions and then i'm looking at the
resulting densities of the deterministic
systems after
a bunch of time has passed so that's a
different kind of density it's a density
over the deterministic ending states or
deterministic trajectories of the system
from a bunch of initial conditions and i
think there has been work done on
characterizing those densities but again
i doubt that those densities are
parametrically defined i bet they're
more like approximations like what we
did here but this is something that
honestly i'm not an expert on the lorenz
attractor so that's something that
i should probably just defer that i
don't i don't know much about it but i'm
pretty sure the stochastic lens
attractor doesn't have a neat solution
to the plank equation which is what you
would need to do to get the stationary
density
all right i'm going to ask a pair of
questions from martin and from miguel so
it's awesome thanks both and everybody
in the chat because it's
cool to have this kind of real-time
field feedback so
the first question is from martin
in what way does the markov blanket
emerge here
is it not here at some point and then
later it is so the first question for
martin is what do you mean by emergence
and then the second
question by miguel is
it is impressive that you can find a
markov blanket in a non-linear system
have you quantified how precise are the
approximations of the covariance and
hessian values each comparing against
numerical simulations so question one
in what way does the markov blanket
emerge question two how precise are the
approximation of the covariance and
hessian
yeah okay so that's a good question um
first question about the emergence
the mark huff blankets
is defined with respect to the
stationary density
the the conditional independence
relationships expressed in those two
upper right
panels log covariance and log hessian so
those things
do temporally vary
in the sense that if you condition on
some initial state
the time varying densities
will
will have different log covariance and
log hessian matrices this idea of
conditioning on an initial
state and then looking at the time
evolving densities that's exactly the
whole point of this paper by thomas and
a few other of us called memory and
markup blankets where
the markov blanket
can change in the sense that if you look
at the evolution of conditional
densities conditioned on some
perturbation those conditional densities
do change but if we just look at the
stationary density by definition the
stationary density doesn't change its
sufficient statistics over time
because it isn't defined with respect to
time you've marginalized out sequences
of variables so in this sense the markov
blanket
if you don't condition on a on a
particular state and you're un you're
just looking at the unconditional
stationary density then it's just always
there it doesn't emerge and maybe i said
emerge
and i didn't mean that in a temporal
sense so there's no sense in which the
markov blanket emerges markup blanket is
just a property of the stationary
covariance matrix or more specifically
its inverse and that is a constant
value that is just a characteristic of
the full six dimensional multivariate
gaussian
so even if we didn't even think about
stochastic processes if i just wrote
down
a six dimensional multivariate gaussian
with these particular entries of the
covariance matrix that is the constant
markup blanket that just always exists
um
the
second question was about
the precision of the covariance and
hessian
numerical simulations
that's a really good question and i'm
assuming was that from one of the
comments that was from miguel yes from
about yes so i'm assuming you mean um
the overlap between
the the um
cover the empirically measured
covariance in the laplace
sorry in the real stochastic lorenz
system and that one measured um or in
that one estimated
in the
um
in like so the one estimated from the
real system and then the analytic
hessian from the stick from the
laplacian rates approximate stochastic
lorenz so i have
i have the paper up here that i can show
this that's a really good question so
one of the reviewers actually asked us
something very similar and we have an
extra figure
that demonstrates exactly that
can you still see my screen yep looks
good okay perfect so
here we're essentially doing exactly
that um comparison where we're looking
at the partial correlation which in the
case of gaussians is actually the same
thing as the hessian which is an
interesting
or sorry it's not the same thing as the
hessian the partial correlation
is uh is
the same is at the same measure of
conditional independence
um
it's not the case for non-gaussians it's
a case for a few classes of exponential
distributions that if you measure the
partial correlation which is a kind of
conditional correlation between two
variables it's the same as the the
corresponding value of the hessian
so what we're doing here is exactly that
we're basically measuring how well the
empirically measured partial correlation
between different subsets of states so
here the third and the sixth states
which should be
these are the two internal states of two
mini lorenz attractors within the full
system so this is like internal state of
brain one internal state of brain two
how their partial correlation actually
measures up with the true hessian value
and it kind of converges to about very
close to zero which agrees with the
analytically
measured hessian so you can basically
quantify this more coarsely by just
looking at the structure of the hessian
matches the empirically measured partial
correlation and the partial correlation
was basically measured for increasing
segments of time so the partial
correlation measured here was from the
first 50 time steps and then up to years
the cumulative partial correlation from
the first until the 500th time step and
so on so basically by looking at the
partial correlation in increasingly long
windows of time it should converge to
the true value of the conditional
independence and
um it approximates that which we get
from the laplace approximated system
what i should say however is that this
partial correlation was not measured
from the full
um lorenz attractor the stochastic one
but actually just from our approximation
so we're just saying that if we make
this approximation and then empirically
measure the partial correlation from
real
um from realizations of that approximate
system
the the empirical measurements line up
with what it should be given the way
that we parameterize the flow using the
polynomial expansion
um
however what we haven't done but i think
would be very interesting and maybe this
is what was being asked in the question
is actually to measure this from the
real stochastic lorenz system to see if
there actually is a markov blanket
in the
um real in in the real around system the
only issue with that is we can't
necessarily use partial correlation if
we did it in the real stochastic lorenz
system because as we were just
discussing like martin asked
do we know what the stationary density
of the real lorenz system is the
stochastic one if we don't know that we
would have to use a less parametric
method like mutual information
conditional mutual information in order
to assess the presence or absence of
conditional independence so it would be
harder to do just because evaluating
massive
conditional information mutual
information for increasing amounts of
time is computationally difficult but i
agree that that is something that should
um be done but no we didn't do do it for
the real stochastic lens we just did it
between our approximation and our
analytic hessian
i hope that answers the question and
that was clear i can
we can
keep talking if there's
any lack of clarity on that
i think continue with the presentation
and if anyone has more questions at the
end of the presentation we'll return to
them okay cool
yeah but that was a very um a good point
is actually measuring the markov blanket
like empirically
okay so the i'm almost done with the the
overview of the paper so the last big
thing that's kind of tucked into the one
of the results section is something
called the sparse coupling conjecture
which is important because it
dissociates conditional independence
from causality so conditional
independence as we said in the context
of a gaussian
actually no it's not even for gaussian
systems for all systems
conditional independence is determined
by
a zero entry in the hessian so if the
hessian between two states is zero which
means the conditional densities don't
change as you change
like the conditional density over one
variable doesn't change as a function of
the other
then
it implies this relationship which is
shown in terms of the jacobian on the
left the jacobian basically measures
causal coupling we we can go into what
it means mathematically but you can just
think of the jacobi the jacobian is the
derivative of the flow function with
respect to the states and the g and
entries in the jacobian that are
non-zero mean that one state is
influencing another so what this
relationship shows is that
if at most one state influences the
other but not otherwise
like there's a non-reciprocal coupling
between one state and the other then the
two states are conditionally
um independent i.e there's a markov
blanket that's a really weird
counterintuitive statement it means that
if i'm affecting you but you're not
affecting me then we will be
conditionally independent in the steady
state
and this is what's called the sparse
coupling conjecture and it's the way we
originally wrote it it was actually much
stronger
of a claim and then we realized there's
actually some conditions on it so it's
called a conjecture because it doesn't
always hold but there's certain
conditions under which it should hold
given a high dimensional enough and
non-linear enough system
um so we can kind of prove that more
mathematically by saying if you expand
the jacobian by basically taking the
derivative of the helmholtz
decomposition so that's what's shown in
the middle thing
and then you um
assume that certain z entries of the
jacobian are zero
then you can basically show that it
implies or sorry not certain entries of
the jacobian but certain products of
entries in the jacobian are zero that it
implies that there's an accompanying
zero entry in the hessian which is shown
on the bottom
so what's shown on the bottom more
specifically is what's known as the
normal form of the flow or kind of a
circular coupling where if you have this
particular structure of the flow
operator where certain um block or
certain sub matrices of the flow
operator are zero then you're guaranteed
to have this kind of sparse coupling um
which means that one state can influence
the other and not vice versa and then
you'll get conditional independence in
the steady state so that's another big
result that um
i think during the earlier live stream
when we talked with lance he had an
example in his paper where that was also
the case where basically two systems
were uh two one state was affecting the
other but they're actually conditionally
independent
um that's that's a uh basically we
rigorously showed the conditions under
which that exists here so just because
you see a zero in the hessian that means
don't assume that the systems can't
affect each other two systems are
conditionally independent doesn't
necessarily mean that they don't affect
each other through
having a non-zero entry in the jacobian
but it just means that those connections
have to be asymmetric or non-reciprocal
so this is an example
physically of what that would look like
say we had some system
with external sensory and active states
under the normal form of the flow with
which is this special block diagonal
flow operator what this essentially
means is that you can get this sparse
coupling conjecture
his sparse coupling conjecture holds as
long as sensory states do not affect
internal states
and active states
do not affect external states directly
but only through
the
sensory states so that's a particular
instantiation of the normal form of the
flow where you have these
basically particular entries of the
jacobian and the solenoidal flow
operator are zero and then you'll get
this
this kind of
sparse coupling or
circular coupling
one question on that
and then dean if you'd like to ask any
questions and this is also related to
the work of miguel the paper that was
brought up earlier
what is the topology of perception
cognition and action is it just
sense influencing internal and internal
influencing active and active
influencing external which then feedback
to sensory sort of the simple clock
model
or here we have a edge between sense and
active states the blanket states and so
in free energy principle and active
inference are we committed to a certain
topology of action
um that's a really good question yeah so
given the sparse coupling conjecture and
the normal form of the flow
all
all this is so basically no we're not
committed to anything there's so many
different combinations that will give
rise to
a conditional synchronization manifold
that can be interpreted as bayesian
mechanics
what all we're saying is that
this coupling structure we have here is
mainly defined by the lack of certain
connections
so all that we're saying is if external
states do not affect active states
and sensory states
or sorry internal states do not directly
affect sensory states so it's the lack
of those two connections can you see my
mouse actually
uh yes
yes so if you don't have a connection
going from blue to red
and you don't have one going from
blue to sensory
but anything else is is is allowed like
all i'm saying is putting constraints on
what cannot exist
then the conditions laid out here
will hold
and the sparse coupling conjecture
um will exist which means that an
asymmetric relationship implies
conditional independence so given that
what it means is that actually
sensory states will be conditionally
independent of uh of internal states
conditioned on active states because
there's only a unidirectional coupling
so those are some weird um
weird like results from this is that
sensory and internal will be
conditionally independent because one
affects the other but the other does not
affect the first one and likewise for
active and uh and
external states but all that being aside
external and and internal will still be
conditionally independent and therefore
there'll still be a synchronization map
between them so
these the conditions about the topology
that i laid out the absence of these
connections just have to do with
satisfying the normal form of the flow
as laid out here and satisfying this
weird sparse coupling conjecture about
unidirectional non-reciprocal coupling
but other than that the active inference
story and the bayesian mechanics story
you can swap around all these
influences and it'll still pertain as
long as this guy is conditionally
independent of this one
so if these two are conditionally
independent
um
dependent on the blanket states then
that synchronization map still exists
but you can have all kinds of weird
coupling loops between the between the
two
thanks very
interesting
dean you want to ask anything here or
well there's so many things i could ask
and i probably and and i'd get a great
answer back and and i'd only be able to
use a small percentage of the great
answer one thing i i do want to i i will
ask this and i'm not sure if it's
if it's good or not but i i've been
doing a lot of work and trying to see
whether or not the active sensory state
is a form of kind of decomposition of
where a concept might rest between
things like content
and context
and i'm just wondering when you when you
do this math and you get a sense
of
knowing what you're working with
and the relationship between all of the
different components of what you're
working with
do you see
in in this a lot instead of things
always assuming that things just sort of
pop out as an emergency as an emergence
do you do you start getting a sense that
sometimes things just exist within and
between and those constraints and
some of the things you talked in terms
of linearity and just getting an
understanding of what you're working
with
do you see
things like concepts
sort of resting in between
these
these other areas we call them in this
diagram external and internal states but
would a concept be that
sort of fluid and appearing and
disappearing based on some of the things
that you've looked at here in this paper
yeah i definitely think so i mean for me
when i start thinking about concepts i
immediately start thinking about
relationships right like what we've
shown here a very low dimensional
systems where you have a few internal a
few active a few sensory
a few external once you start having
larger
higher dimensional systems so say we
weren't modeling a lorenz a two s like
kind of dumb lorenz attractors just
oscillating around each other but say we
had some 100 dimensional neural network
synchronized with another 100
dimensional external state space like
another neural network once you're
getting into that world
i think you get the you can have the
computational representational capacity
for things like concepts because you
just have a higher correlational
structure so imagine that we had a
hundred internal states
the internal states we know in some way
are relating to the external states but
they're also relating to each other so
there might be like sub groups like
groups of 10 or 20 neurons that are all
correlated and they're firing to each
other there might be rich recurrent
internal dynamics just within the
internal states and the particular
relationship of sub manifolds so to
speak of the internal state space how
those conditionally relate to external
states that's where i think you start
getting into the world of concepts where
you can have
under a certain part of the external
state space this part of the internal
manifold gets more or less activated
versus when that part of the external
state space lights up
this different part of the internal
state space gets lit up so i think the
key to identifying some of the concepts
really relies on having higher
dimensional systems which then allow you
to have kind of more rich
lower dimensional correlation structure
that kind of exists in the ambient
dimension of like 100 dimensional state
space
that that would be that's how i at least
interpret your description of like the
concepts kind of existing in between it
really rests in
lower dimensional manifolds of ambient
high dimensionality
um
so yeah that's like we're pretty much
done with the thing that this is just a
summary of the contributions
um
i would say like yeah it humbles
decomposition fitting it to a stochastic
dynamical system where we don't know the
steady state distribution
and then going through the steps with
this laplace approximated one
studying its synchronization manifold
doing this cool like coupled lorenz
thing and then finally this sparse
coupling conjecture about circular
coupling
um
and yeah you can move to the discussion
now or go back dive into the slides or
dive into different parts of the paper
that i didn't even talk about here
um whatever you guys think
best
great
maybe you could unshare and we'll have
some time just to
talk and see um if anyone else has any
questions in the chat so just one
starting question from martin was
the question above was whether it is
even known that the lorenz attractor has
a stationary state
did we address that earlier oh sorry
yeah we we addressed it like my initial
answer that was i'm pretty sure it's not
known
but i'm not positive like i'm not an
expert on the stochastic level
instructor but i'm pretty sure it's not
known
because i just
imagine intuitively that writing down a
unique solution to the focker plank
operator would be very difficult for
that which i imagine is difficult for
any system that exhibits stochastic
chaos
okay and another question from martin is
whether the sparse coupling conjecture
requires a gaussian as the stationary
distribution
um no it doesn't
um
the requirements on it are not about the
gaussianity of the density
they're more actually
so
for this new paper that's in review now
there's an appendix in that paper that
um more that fleshes out the conditions
on the sparse coupling conjecture more
um rigorously
and the conditions are not about the the
get the
form of the stationary density um
they're actually more about basically
how
local the coupling is in the solenoidal
term so if the solenoidal terms are
state-dependent like solenoidal term ij
depends on the states
then the sparse coupling conjecture only
holds if that dependence is only a
function of states i and j but if the
coupling between states i and j
is actually a state dependent function
of state k
then the sparse coupling conjecture can
be more easily violated
um and i have a proof of that that i can
again share my screen and show you but
it's not really related to your question
which was more about is the gaussianity
related to the sparse coupling so yeah
it's not what you described there
reminds me a lot of neuro modulation and
about how like the effective
connectivity of two regions could be
modulated so
here's a question from miguel and then
we can go to dean and then i have a
question as well so from miguel in
non-linear systems high order
correlations might arise
i think this means the hessian may not
be enough to assess conditional
independence do you see a way to explore
that with this method
um
my
yeah that's a great question so my
intuition
is that if you use this method that we
talked about in the second part
um
where it's like higher order density
learning
if you
are basically basically the high order
density learning where you're not
assuming a laplace approximation but
you're enforcing a
state space local
quadratic approximation
to the potential function
that means that you have a hessian
that's changing over state space
what your point is basically saying is
that because of higher order
correlations there will probably be
parts of state space even if for like
three quarters of space space the
hessian is zero there's a final quarter
where the hessian will not be zero in
that part of state space
and i think what that allows you to do
is basically say
that insofar as the hessian does locally
approximate the markov blanket between
two states it means that there's
regions of state space where the markov
blanket condition applies and then other
regions where it doesn't and the markup
blanket disappears
the claims in this paper about
the conditional independence
relationships especially as they relate
to sparse coupling only apply
to hessians that even if they're state
dependent hessians which implies a
non-gaussian stationary distribution
that that entry of the hessian is zero
for every part in state space
so i don't know if the sparse coupling
conjecture for instance applies
um where there's a state-dependent
hessian entry that's
not that zero in some parts of state
space and non-zero and other parts i
think that will throw a wrench in this
formulation potentially
um but it would be interesting to say if
if you can still interpret
the entry of the hessian as being
a on off signal of there's a markov
blanket between these two things what
does it mean if that markup link is
changing as a function of where you are
in state space does it mean that
sometimes there's a synchronization map
between these two states depending if
they're visiting this region of state
space versus that or maybe that actually
doesn't make sense so i don't know i
think it can certainly be used to
explore those questions but offhand i
don't have an easy answer i think that's
a really good good question
cool thank you
dean if you'd like to throw one out
yeah i'm just curious so we had a we
were just doing a recent paper and it
was talking about
sort of how did you get here how did you
come to this place and i would like to
ask
connor
when i don't know
the history of how housekeeping
uh was introduced to this formalism so i
was just wondering if maybe you could
walk us through that i don't think you
sort of
put a put a notice up on the door and
called housekeeping it just seemed to
insert itself so maybe you could tell us
how that how you know when it was
introduced
not assumed right how you kind of dealt
with that
yeah yeah it's a a really a good
question so basically
well okay yeah it's interesting
um
the whole point so from my understanding
the evolution of this paper
came into
um that the beginnings of this paper was
there was a a meeting that i presented
at carl's lab meeting in 20
must have been late 2020
where i was trying to do this kind of
bayes mechanical analysis on a very high
dimensional non-linear system and i was
trying to model basically schools of
fish can you look at certain
groups of a big school of fish and
interpret their states as if they're
doing inference about something
happening on the other side of the
school
and so at the end we had a bunch of
conversations i think we had three
meetings total where we just went
through the mathematics of how that's
possible and it drove carl to say okay
what we're going to do is we're going to
write down we're going to write a paper
where we deal with a system like that
where things are very state dependent
and non-linear and state space so that
forced carl basically to go back to the
drawing board with the helmholtz
decomposition
and as a result of all the mathematical
formulation here which is like 95
percent just carl like
writing that down and figuring things
out he realized that there's this extra
term this housekeeping term that pops
out of the helmholtz decomposition
so my assumption is he named it
housekeeping term because it was
basically this um
unintended side effect of trying to do
the helmholtz decomposition on systems
that are highly non-linear and so the
housekeeping term
came out as like oh i need to have this
thing to make sure everything's neat and
in order because if you actually look at
the mathematical derivation of where
that term comes from i'm not sure carl
was familiar with it
from the literature or if he just
derived it and kind of thought of it
himself i'm actually really not sure on
his own
intellectual journey to getting there
but it is in the stochastic processes
literature it's not like a totally new
thing it's been known for like decades
now
but i think from his perspective he
labeled it housekeeping term because it
was this new thing that pops out that he
has to
account for that keeps the full
plank solution like in order so you
basically need to add that on to make
sure that certain terms don't be
like remain zero when you're trying to
solve the or punic solution it has
to do something
called the probability current to make
sure the divergence of the probability
current to zero need to add in this
housekeeping term so my
interpretation of the word housekeeping
is very analogous to the word correction
like it's a correction term or a
cancellation term
um but that was a a vocabulary that carl
just started using in the paper
awesome dot 4 32.4 it's never too late
um
you briefly touched on where i was going
to go with this next question which was
about collective behavior so just
how are you thinking about these kinds
of formalisms in collective behavioral
systems
are we thinking about multi-agent
simulations of active inference agents
like we had done with ants or is there
another level of analysis where the
collective is sort of this
shifting
entity in and of itself like where does
this apply to collective behavior
yeah that's a great question so um i i
can just personally speak to that
because that's like essentially the
the
thing i'm doing during my phd so one
half of my phd or say one third of my
phd is doing the first thing which is
very similar to what you've done with uh
active inference where i'm just taking a
bunch of active inference agents and i'm
making them school together
i first tried doing that and like that's
a separate story that like maybe we can
have another live stream and talk about
that because that's a cool thing but
that has nothing to do with writing down
the stationary density of the entire
system i tried to do that at first but
it's very hard because every active
inference agent is a mixture between
sdes and odes and all the things we
talked about today were just sdes
stochastic systems when whereas when
you're doing a single active inference
agent like doing predictive coding
its neural dynamics are actually solved
as an ode which is a straight
deterministic gradient descent on
variational free energy so in a big
collective
dynamical system that has some odes and
some sdes writing down the stationary
density becomes very difficult so
because of that we had all these
meetings and this paper was one of the
results of those meetings so the the
approach i'm taking now is i'm not
modeling individuals as active inference
agents i'm just modeling each of them as
like for instance the 2d position of a
particle that has some velocity and some
position and then there's classic
schooling models like the v-check model
or the reynolds model or the cousin
model which was um identified by my
advisor
where you're basically just trying to
model
schooling fish or
schooling or flocking birds as a bunch
of little stochastic differential
equations that are coupled to each other
so the approach i'm taking now is
applying exactly the formalism
described today
to higher dimensional systems and you
encounter special challenges when you do
that because
um
the trying to fit a polynomial expansion
with all the higher order interaction
terms to like a hundred dimensional
system it's just not going to be
feasible if you're including every
possible interaction it's just like
you're going to have an ex
combinatorially explosive state space so
i'm basically a lot of the work i'm
doing now is figuring out ways to fit
the helmholtz decomposition using
non-polynomial expansion methods that
are more
um
uh amenable to higher dimensional data
where you don't have this cursive
dimensionality and so a lot of that
involves what you could probably guess
using amortized approximations like deep
neural networks to fit the coefficients
of the helmholtz
um so that's something i'm like
literally working on right now so
there's not too many results on there
but that's like that's one of the two
directions i'm going there's the
multi-agent active inference and then
there's the high dimensional helmholtz
decomposition stuff
cool like i'd imagine that nested
cognitive systems with shifting
boundaries and functional relationships
that's challenging for any framework but
at least
we're quite rapidly approaching
the ability to have the grammar and the
motifs
to actually talk about those questions
and then also see them from multiple
perspectives
either as
uh cognitive agents interacting in a way
where we don't even need to have the top
level be anything specific or more from
a top-down perspective which as you
pointed out it's hard to then introduce
the cognitive elements into those
particles
yeah exactly
yeah i mean just if i could just follow
up on that i think the ultimate goal
would be to bridge both right like it
would be sick to write down a big
multi-agent active inference simulation
where every single agent is actually
doing a gradient descent on free energy
to choose their actions whether they're
mdps or predictive coding agents but
then you can also write down a
stationary density for the whole thing
and identify the markov blanket of the
whole system because then you would
truly have the multi-scale perspective
you would have the generative model of
the individuals and then you would have
the generative model of the whole
existing simultaneously and then you
could really ask questions like if i
change the sensory precision of this
single agent how does that affect the
actual markov blanket at the collective
level and that's just so like
technically difficult that's like
originally what i planned to do
but i ended up splitting into two
separate things because just the
mathematics behind it was too hard for
me but uh yeah that would be really cool
i i hope this isn't uh misleading
physical intuition but it's almost like
if we have a ball rolling on a surface
there um could be the sort of particles
within the ball which are
minimizing a potential function relative
to their local position and then there's
the ball rolling on the landscape and
then the housekeeping term is almost
like the landscape is soft and so it's
state dependent what the landscape
actually looks like that's why you can't
just set it and forget it with the way
that the
landscape is the flow operator are
dean if you have a question and then
martin i have a question from him
yeah uh so
on on that
you
on that
same theme
uh i'll i'll give you a sort of a
metaphorical story so if i'm standing on
the bunny hill and i'm trying to control
gravity
and i'm sliding with all my friends
we're flocking down here on the bunny
hill and having a good time and we're
looking up at the head wall
and the irony is of course if you've
been up there mathematically you know
that you can't control gravity on the
head wall just because the pitch is
different now to the person on the bunny
hill
what and all of their behavior they're
all kind of swimming around down here on
the sort of more gradual surface
conceptually
they would have to let go of their
concepts of what they're doing to
control gravity down here those those
same themes don't apply on that on that
head wall
how how do we get our minds wrapped
around that the letting go of what we
think
we would our first intuition
we we can see the head wall we're not
even blinded to it our first intuition
would be well how will i control gravity
up there when in fact the first thing
you have to do is let go of your current
concept right so mathematically how
would we
how would we show
that the benefit isn't in in in a
continuation or uh
a common combinatorial thinking around
that it would actually be a
reconciliation letting go of what you
know in order to be able to take up
something
new that's the part where
i'm not sure if your paper answers that
but at least it leaves enough space open
that it isn't a lin always a linear
i'm down here
i'm gonna i'm gonna make my way up the
side of that that hill and i'm going to
be able to apply exactly the same
thinking to that new situation
that's the part that i quite fascinating
i i really appreciate
the idea of collective behavior but for
me it's how do i let go of one idea in
order to be able to take up a new one
that allows me to continue to fep my way
down the hill um yeah that's really cool
yeah no i think that's like a critical
i i would say that's a critical insight
from all of this is showing that like
something that seems optimal at your
local level or whatever the concepts are
they use at your local level really it's
a different game when you zoom out or
when you look at like a different
um scale so i think that has a lot to do
with this idea of what me and daniel
were just talking about of like
how do the individuals their their
language that the terms the state space
they think in terms of could be a
totally fundamentally different language
than the language that the collective
thinks in terms of which is the same
thing of like
me trying to plan now versus playing in
the future planning now is based on
making sure like i am sitting up
straight and i'm drinking enough water
but playing in the futures what am i
going to do in 10 days and what's
optimal from those perspectives can be
like a totally different
state space like a different language
essentially
so the nesting of different time skills
is important and also it's one reason
the housekeeping term is important
because for active systems that can
undertake epistemic actions
if action is not recalculated every
single perception cognitive and action
loop then it's like you're going to be
navigating based upon
a mirage or a fantasy
let me ask this good question from
martin in the chat
the construction in this paper of how
internal states do inference on external
states is still the same as in a free
energy principle for a particular
physics or not
is miguel's criticism of the derivation
of this in a free energy principle for a
particular physics taken into account
here or not
um
that's a really good question so
my understanding um
okay so the big thing that changed
between free energy principle for a
particular physics
and what was done here as well as what
was done in lance's paper
on the biggest
change and i think i'm not sure miguel
you if miguel's here he can correct me
if miguel also made this is we went from
arg max to expectation so in free energy
persons
uh
free energy principle for a particular
physics the synchronization manifold was
defined as a map between the modes of
two conditional densities i.e the
maximum probability
point to another max probability point
the big move that um allows us to get
away with the difference between argamax
and
um expectation is that we make
everything gaussian so that they're the
same and crucially everything is
differentiable because gaussians are
smooth and and the arg max function is
crucially smooth because the expectation
is smooth so i don't know
how you get around
how you deal with multimodal densities
um when you're mapping between the modes
of the two conditional densities because
the arg max function
may not be differentiable anymore
and one of the main things that and the
differentiability of arg max slash
expectation also
factors into the differentiability of
the synchronization manifold which needs
to be differentiable
by construction so i think one of the
main things that
miguel was talking about was talking
about the differentiability of sigma
but he was also talking about the the
flow of the internal states and whether
the flow of the internal states can also
be thought of as doing flows on
variational free energy and that paper
they very very nicely showed that the
average flow is not the same as the flow
of the average and therefore it's not
guaranteed that any
individual realization will look as if
it's doing
inference so the these this this paper
as well as lance's paper on basic
mechanics that does not say anything
basically about
the the direction of the flow so i don't
think there's any disagreement there um
in the new paper that's coming out we
actually do directly have a new
um result that talks about the flow of
individual trajectories that will more
specifically address
the flow-based argument that miguel was
making in uh in his paper where we're
actually looking at the flow of an
individual trajectory of the system
in terms of gradients of
the surprisal function or gradients of
the variational free energy
and we're doing that from different
marginals of the steady state density so
the flow the active states
as a gradient descent on the um
variational free energy of the
particular states for instance or the
blanket states
um but but like so so there's multiple
things that can be
answered from your question one has to
do with the differentiability of sigma
which relies on the differentiability of
things like arc max versus expectation
and other things have to do with
you relying on the differentiability of
sigma to look at the flow of the um
most likely internal state given blanket
states and neither of these papers
actually have to do with the flow
argument and whether the average flows
equal the flow of the average they just
have to do with on average does the most
likely internal say given blanket states
parameterize the density and that is is
the case that's mathematically the case
and it also gets around the arg max
versus expectation um issue by making
everything doubt soon
um are there other issues is there
something more specific because there
are several critiques in miguel's paper
i think that and maybe i didn't get at
the one that you're talking about
uh martin i think this is a perfect
place for either of you to have a last
word conor though
thanks so much for
scheduling this for breaking into the
dot 3 tier
which was
unexpected but awesome and we really
look forward to your future work and
joining us for future discussions so any
last comments if you would like to have
them
um yeah no thanks so much for having me
on it's been it's been a real pleasure
there's been a really stimulating
conversation it's and it's also thanks
to miguel and martin who were in the and
whoever else was watching it just really
appreciate the comments that was really
nice and uh and he also just general
apologies on the part of all the authors
that they couldn't be here today and
also for the earlier live streams
uh on this paper but you did a really
great job in discussing the paper
um so yeah it's it's really cool to like
that we put out the paper and then we
get this attention and we get this
chance to like talk about this stuff
with you so thanks and thanks dean for
your great questions too it's really
always fun uh chatting with you on here
i think you were here at the last one as
well that i was
at so yeah yeah it's awesome and just
like wow
eight hours is not enough to explore and
there could be so many ways to
connect what's being said to core terms
and the active inference ontology and
it's just a great title so thank you
connor thank you dean and everybody who
is participating live and asynchronously